RAFAEL JOSE NEGRETTE AMAYA

Senior Software Developer

Cel +57-3024787541

rafaelnegretteamaya@outlook.com

www.linkedin.com/in/rafael-negrette-650a12b8

Metropolitan Area of Barranquilla, Colombia

PROFILE

As a seasoned software developer, I specialize in crafting robust Java solutions. My expertise encompasses the Spring Framework and various databases, complemented by familiarity with CI/CD practices. I have substantial experience with cloud platforms, having contributed significantly to projects focused on migrating legacy applications to GCP and adding features to other applications on AWS. Over the past decade, I have played pivotal roles in teams tasked with application analysis, design, development, implementation, enhancement, and testing.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Perficient Backend Software Developer

December 2021 - Present Bogota, D.C., Capital District, Colombia

- Contributed to all stages of the software development lifecycle from requirements gathering to deployment of the system, this involved the use of Google Cloud Kubernetes.
- Designed and implemented reactive APIs using Spring WebFlux to enhance application throughput and scalability in high-load Spring Boot services.
- Implemented two-factor authentication by integrating third-party security validations into a spring boot service using security best practices.
- Applied API First Approach to develop new applications in the microservice ecosystem using OpenAPI specification.
- Responsible for designing, and implementing client features with at least 80% of code coverage and acceptance tests in CI/CD pipeline.
- Ensuring quality of the developed features on the delivery of release products through regression testing with the TestNG framework.
- Maintained Spring microservice applications by adding enhancements and resolving production defects to ensure system stability.

Prodigious Latin America Senior Software Engineer

April 2021 - December 2021 Bogota, D.C., Capital District, Colombia

- Responsible for designing, writing code with unit test cases, and providing support to web applications.
- Working independently, assuming ownership of the design, interface, and programming of simple and complex web applications.
- Provide estimates for tasks and assume ownership of these estimates.
- Working with web applications with back-end Java technologies for modular applications (OSGi).
- Implement user and business requirements which are composed of multiple development activities or touch various sub-systems.

Tata Consultancy Services Java Oracle Developer

December 2019 - April 2021 Bogota, D.C., Capital District, Colombia

- Developed the client requirement in the SLA-defined time, using Spring Framework, Hibernate, Spring Flow, and Spring Rest, achieving the requirements of the User Acceptance Test.
- Applied the Principia of agile methodology, continuous integration, continuous deployment, and tools like bitbucket, improving the shipping process of the product.
- Migrated and integrated related applications through database-automatized scripts and merge code using git workflow strategies.

Conexia

Programmer Analyst

May 2019 – December 2019 Bogotá D.C. Area, Colombia

> • Developed requirements of the scheduling module of the client, using Java EE, Hibernate, and Primefaces, achieving the requirements of the User Acceptance

Test.

- Applied the Principia of agile methodology, integration, and unit test tool with a team of more than twenty members, improving the software quality.
- Developed some of the requirements of the affiliation's module following functional analyst specifications, with a development team of 7 persons following scrum methodology.

Stackpointer
Maintenance and Development Engineer
July 2011 – April 2019
Barranguilla, Colombia

- Developed the backend of multi-tenancy applications with spring boot.
- Set up a development server with docker for the backend developers to work more easily with the frontend developers.
 - Integrated 5 logistics-related applications in one container application for the administration of access and profiles of the users of all 5 applications.
- Developed the backend of the container application using Spring Boot and Hibernate for the persistence layer to ease the development with the team.
- Developed, optimized, and made changes in several Java EE applications to be deployed in the application server Weblogic of the client.
- Used different technologies and languages such as Javascript, Jquery, EJB and Eclipselink (mapped entities with the relational database) to develop several functionalities of the applications.
- Designed and optimized several SQL queries for the Oracle database reducing the response time of the applications.

PUBLICATIONS

• ICAI 2022. Communications in Computer and Information Science, A Wayuunaiki Translator to Promote Ethno-Tourism Using, Deep Learning Approaches (https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-19647-8_21)

EDUCATION

- Universidad de La Guajira, Bachelor's degree, System Engineer (2005 2011)
- Universidad de Bogotá Jorge Tadeo Lozano, Master's Degree in Engineering and Data Analytics (2019 - 2022)

CERTIFICATIONS

- AWS Certified: Cloud Practitioner (2023). Have a fundamental understanding of IT services and their uses in the AWS Cloud.
- Oracle Certified Professional: Java SE 11 Developer (2021). Exhibited thorough and broad knowledge of the Java programming language, coding practices, and utilization of new features incorporated into Java SE 11.
- Certified Big Data Engineer (2018). Has demonstrated proficiency in designing and utilizing Big Data solutions (using Hadoop, MapReduce, and other tools).
- Oracle Database SQL Certified Expert (2016). Has demonstrated the skills required to work with the powerful SQL programming language and has mastered the key concepts of a relational database.

LANGUAGES

- Ingles (Professional Working)
- Spanish (Native or Bilingual)

TECHNOLOGIES AND PROGRAMMING LANGUAGES

- Java, Hibernate, Spring Boot, Spring MVC, Restful web Services, Spring Cloud, gRPC and Spring WebFlux.
- Junit, Integration Test, Test Driven Development, Git, Subversion, TeamCity, Urban Deploy, Artifactory, TestNG, TestContainers and Wiremock.
- Sql, Oracle, postgresql, Ms SqlServer, Jquery, css, html5, javascript, postman and React.
- Linux Shell, Weblogic application Server, Tomcat, WebSphere IBM, AWS (EC2, S3, AIM, DynamoDB, ECS), and GCP (Spanner, GKE).